Manuel E. Gondra Manuscript Collection:
Calendar of the Manuel E. Gondra Manuscript Collection, The University of Texas Library, prepared by Carlos Eduardo Castañeda, University of Texas, and Jack Autrey Dabbs, AM College of Texas. México: Editorial Jus, 1952.
- Eighteenth Century Documents (1778-1799)
  - 1737 Pino Manrrique, Juan del. [Carta a José de Gálvez dando cuenta de su visita de inspección a Tarija.] Potosí, August 16, 1785. 19 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 110-1-7-H. (Box [MG 1053])
    Origin and customs of Chiriguanos; settlements by Luis de Fuentes; Charayes (Xarayes?); La Concepción; comparison with Hernán Cortés; fertility of Tarija; products of la Recoleta; poverty of the Lipes, Chichas, and Cintí; Tucumán; comparison with los Batuecos; monasteries of Santo Domingo, San Agustín, and San Juan de Dios; character of the armed expeditions; tax-supported military regime recommended; utilization of ex-Jesuit property; jurisdiction of the Audiencia of Charcas; Portuguese designs on Peru; need to explore and conquer the Gran Chaco.
    Printed: MLB 43-44, (folios 7v-8 only).
  - 1738 Melo de Portugal, Pedro. Relacion individual del actual estado de esta Provincia del Paraguay... mes de Julio, hasta el presente,... en conformidad de la Real orden de 10 de mayo de 84. Asunción, December 31, 1785. 2 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 122-6-1-A. (Box [MG 1573])
  - 1739 Velasco, Luis de. Sumario de las Alajas de Plata y ornamentos de las Iglesias de Españoles del Paraguay Segun la visita gral. de su Obispo año de 1785. 1 l. 23 × 33 cm. f. 50. Modern copy from AGI 123-6-10. (Box [MG 2058c])
  - 1740 _____. Sumario de las alajas de plata, y Hornamentos, de las Iglesias de Indios del Paraguay.... 1 l. 23 × 33 cm. f. 51. Modern copy from AGI 123-6-10. (Box [MG 2058d])
  - 1741 Jesús María, Carlos de. [Certificado de mal salud del obispo Luis de Velasco.] Asunción, January 5, 1786. 2 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 52-53. Modern copy from AGI 123-6-10. (Box [MG 2058e])
  - 1742 Martí y Ruiz, José. [Certificado de mal salud del obispo Luis de Velasco.] Asunción, January 6, 1786. 2 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 53v-54. Modern copy from AGI 123-6-10. (Box [MG 2058f])
  - 1743 Velasco, Luis de. [Carta a S. M. en que escribe larga relación sobre el estado material de la Iglesia, el Arzobispado, el Clero Secular y Regular, las Monjas, el Seminario, las Iglesias Cofradías y lugares píos y estado del Pueblo.] Asunción, January 13, 1786. 47 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 1-47. Modern copy from AGI 123-6-10. (Box [MG 2058a])
    Answer to cédula of July 1, 1770; contains data from 1547 but emphasis is on the contemporary conditions of church in Paraguay.
  - 1744 _____. Demostracion de la renta que ha correspondido á la Silla Episcopal, Fabricas de Iglesia, Curas Rectores de ella, Sacristan, y Curas de la Villa Rica del Espiritu Santo, y de San Isidro Labrador de Curuguatí, Segun lo producido de los Remates de Diezmos en el quinquenio de los años de 1781 hasta el de 1785 inclusive. Asunción, January 13, 1786. 3 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 47-49. Modern copy from AGI 123-6-10. (Box [MG 2058b])
  - 1745 _____. [Carta a S. M. comunicando la remisión de la relación de su visita general y suplicando ser transferido a otra iglesia.] Asunción, January 13, 1786. 2 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 55-56. Modern copy from AGI 123-6-10. (Box [MG 2058g])
    Bad health of Velasco.
  - 1746 PUNTOS PROPUESTOS EN LA PRIMERA JUNTA CELEBRADA SOBRE EL SUBSIDIO ECLESIÁSTICO. A FAVOR DE NUESTRO SOVERANO MONARCA EL DIA 23 DE ENERO DE ESTE AÑO DE 1786 EN EL PALACIO EPISCOPAL.... Asunción, January 23, 1786. 8 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 20-27. Modern copy from AGI 123-6-13-A, with two typewritten copies, each 3 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 289d])
    Doubts raised by group and decisions reached. Attended by the bishop, the governor, the minister of the royal hacienda, and the archdeacon and presentor of the cathedral. The junta consisted of Pedro Melo de Portugal, Martín José de Aramburu, Antonio de la Peña, and Pedro Zamudio. From copy made by Francisco Antonio Amansio González on April 6, 1786.
  - 1747 González de Escobar, Francisco Amansio. [Auto en que declara las sumas que se deben cobrar de varios curas en cumplimiento de la orden para el cobro del subsidio real eclesiástico.] Asunción, January 25, 1786. 6 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 4-9. Modern copy from AGI 123-6-13-B, with two typewritten copies, each 4 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 331b])
  - 1748 Melo de Portugal, Pedro. [Carta a José de Gálvez contando las dificultades encontradas en la cobranza de los dos millones de ducados de los eclesiásticos, así como la relación del valor de sus rentas.] Asunción, February 13, 1786. 3 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 1-3. Modern copy from AGI 123-6-13-B, with two typewritten copies, each 2 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 331a])
  - 1749 Velasco, Luis de. [Carta del Obispo del Paraguay sobre los méritos de los principales eclesiásticos de la diócesis.] Asunción, February 13, 1786. 7 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 122-3-18-A. (Box [MG 862])
    Antonio de la Peña, Gavino Echevarría y Gallo, Pedro Regalado de Almada, and Juan Antonio de Zavala.
  - 1750 Barrientes, Pedro Nolasco. Aprobacion [de la patente de Antonio Bogarín.] Convento grande de la Asunción, March 11, 1786. 2 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 7v-8. Modern copy from AGI 123-7-25-B, with two typewritten copies, each 1 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 334d])
    Instructions for work among Tobas Indians of Gran Chaco.
  - 1751 González Escobar, Francisco Amansio. Estracto de las cantidades liquidas del subsidio exigible conforme á las actuaciónes del Subdelegado Don Francisco Antonio Amansio Gonzalez. Asunción, April 6, 1786. 9 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 5-13. Modern copy from AGI 123-6-13-A, with two typewritten copies, each 5 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 289b])
    List of contributors and their contributions to royal tax.
  - 1752 _____. Relacion de las partidas de Hacienda que entraron en la Real Caxa del Paraguay por razon del Real subsidio Eclesiastico segun consta del Libro Real de este Ramo. Asunción, April 6, 1786. 2 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 25-26. Modern copy from AGI 123-6-13-A, with two typewritten copies, each 2 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 289e])
    Contributions from 1744-1755.
  - 1753 Melo de Portugal, Pedro. [Carta al Marqués de la Sonora sobre la exacción del donativo de los dos millones de ducados sobre todas las rentas eclesiásticas.] Asunción, April 13, 1786. 4 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 1-4. Modern copy from AGI 123-6-13-A, with two typewritten copies, each 2 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 289a])
    Dispatch of extract by Francisco Amansio González listing contributions to royal treasury.
  - 1754 Velasco, Luis de. [Carta al Marqués de Sonora dando noticia del estado en que se halla la liquidación y exacción del subsidio eclesiástico de este obispado.] Asunción, April 13, 1786. 6 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 14-19. Modern copy from AGI 123-6-13-A, with two typewritten copies, each 4 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 289c])
  - 1755 González Escobar, Francisco Amansio. [Carta a José de Gálvez sobre las discordancias llevadas en el cobro del subsidio real eclesiástico.] Asunción, April 13, 1786. 9 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 27-35. Modern copy from AGI 123-6-13-A, with two typewritten copies, each 5 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 289f])
  - 1756—Pontes, _____ (?). Noticias del Lago Xarayes. 26 p. 21 × 27 cm. April-June 1786. Modern copy from British Museum Add. Mss. 17603 fo: 90. (Box [MG 544])
    Expedition from Bella, Mato Grosso, to explore Lago Xarayes. Continuation to Paraguay River; natural features; description of Lagoa de Uberaba and Lagoa Gaiva.
  - 1757 Amarilla, Bartolomé José and Pedro Martínez. [Carta a S. M. quejándose de los decretos del obispo, Fray Luis de Velasco.] Asunción, May 13, 1786. 7 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 123-6-21-A. (Box [MG 1913])
    Religious life of the province.
  - 1758 CONSEJO DE INDIAS. [Dictamen fiscal sobre la relación del obispo del Paraguay, Luis de Velasco, de la visita general que ha ejecutado, el estado de su salud, y suplicación que se le traslade a otra iglesia.] Madrid, July 30, 1786. 4 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 57-60. Modern copy from AGI 123-6-10. (Box [MG 2058h])
    With fiscal's recommendation that confraternities be disbanded.
  - 1759 Melo de Portugal, Pedro. [Carta al Marqués de Sonora informando sobre la falta de demandas contra Agustín Fernando de Pinedo o sus herederos.] Asunción, September 13, 1786. 2 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 122-5-1. (Box [MG 1954])
  - 1760 _____. [Carta a S. M. en que se cuentan los antecedentes desde 1771 sobre la reedificación de la catedral.] Asunción, November 17, 1786. 21 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 3-23. Modern copy from AGI 123-6-11-A, with two typewritten copies, each 12 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 336b])
    Roles of high civil, military, and ecclesiastical officials; defense of position of Melo de Portugal.
  - 1761 _____. Relación del tiempo experimentado en los seis anteriores meses del presente año y demás particularidades.... Asunción, December (?) 31, 1786. 6 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 146-1-7-B. (Box [MG 1475])
    Progress in cattle raising and agriculture in Paraguay. Same content as No. 1762 infra.
  - 1762 _____. Relación del tiempo experimentado en los seis anteriores meses.... Asunción, December (?) 1786. 7 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 122-6-3-A. (Box [MG 1391])
    Another copy of 1761, [MG 1475] supra.
  - 1763 Buceta Figueroa, José. [Carta al gobernador intendente, Francisco de Biedma, sobre su visita a los pueblos y misiones del Piray, Florida, Cabezas, Abapó, Iguirí, y Tacurís.] Piray, April 4, 1787. 1 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 123-1-13. (Box [MG 1522])
  - 1764 Ludañez, Manuel Ignacio de. [Carta al gobernador intendente, Francisco de Biedma, en que informa sobre el resultado de la comisión de José Buceta, Ingeniero y Comisionado de la tercera división de límites con los dominios portugueses.] Santa Cruz, April 10, 1787. 2 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 123-1-13. (Box [MG 621])
  - 1765 Melo de Portugal, Pedro. [Carta a S. M. sobre competencia sucitada por el Obispo sobre demolición de la Catedral y traslado al templo que fué de los Jesuítas.] Asunción, April 18, 1787. 4 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 123-6-11-B, with two typewritten copies, each 2 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 234])
  - 1766 Biedma, Francisco de. [Carta al Marqués de Sonora sobre trabajos administrativos hechos en la provincia de Cochabamba.] Cochabamba, May 6, 1787. 5 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 1-5. Modern copy from AGI 123-1-13. (Box [MG 1521a])
    Boundaries between Santa Cruz and La Plata.
  - 1767 _____. Extracto de los granos que existen de los que ofrecieron los Hacendados voluntariamente para los Positos establecidos á estimulos del Gobernador Intendente Don Francisco de Biedma dentro de su antigua Provincia (oy Partido de Cochabamba). Cochabamba, May 6, 1787. 1 l. 16 × 22 cm. f. 6. Modern copy from AGI 123-1-13. (Box [MG 1521b])
  - 1768 Carlos III. [Cédula real al virrey del Río de la Plata sobre la competencia ocurrida entre el Obispo y su Cabildo en orden a la iglesia que deben eregir para catedral.] Madrid? May 19, 1787. 2 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 1-2. Modern copy from AGI 123-6-11-A, with two typewritten copies, each 1 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 336a])
  - 1769 Melo de Portugal, Pedro. Relacion del tiempo experimentado en los seis anteriores meses del presente año y demas particularidades.... Asunción, June 30, 1787. 10 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 122-6-4, with another modern copy, 8 l. 17 × 23 cm. from AGI 146-1-7. (Box [MG 1471])
    Ranching and agricultural progress of each city and town of the province.
  - 1770 Biedma, Francisco de. [Carta al Marqués de Loreto sobre misiones de Chiriguanos y Parapití.] Santa Cruz de la Sierra, August 5, 1787. 6 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 110-1-7-D. (Box [MG 1051])
    Work of Francisco del Pilar, Manuel Gil, José de Buceta, José Ayarza, and Francisco Mendiola.
  - 1771 Pino Manrrique, Juan del. [Carta al Marqués de Sonora, sobre fomento del partido de Tarija y población de sus fronteras.] Potosí, August 16, 1787. 1 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 120-5-1. (Box [MG 772])
  - 1772 González y Escobar, Juan Francisco Amansio. [Carta a Juan Lorenzo Gaona.] Paraíso de Melódia, September 3, 1787. 2 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 49v-50. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional [de Asunción?], Vol. 3421. (Box [MG 546bk])
    Plans for settlements at Paraíso.
  - 1773 _____. [Carta a Joaquín de Alós.] Melódia, September 7, 1787. 2 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 18-19. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional [de Asunción?], Vol. 3420. (Box [MG 546z])
    Protection offered families of fugitives from rebel Indian tribes.
  - 1774 _____. [Carta a Joaquín de Alós y Brú.] Melódia, September 9, 1787. 2 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 21-22. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional [de Asunción], Vol. 3420. (Box [MG 546ab])
    Recovery of stolen property from rebel Tencapín.
  - 1775 ASUNCIÓN, CABILDO DE. [Carta a S. M. informando sobre el buen gobierno de Pedro Melo de Portugal con motivo de su retiro y reemplazo por Joaquín Alós.] September 13, 1787. 6 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 123-6-12, with two typewritten copies, each 3 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 235])
    Founding of presidios in the Chaco, Quarepotí, and Iguamandiyú on east bank of Paraguay River. Signed: Juan Valeriano de Ceballos, Francisco Olegario de la Mora, Pedro Nolasco Domecq, Miguel Rubio y Díaz, Vicente Tagle y Rey, Fermín de Arredondo y Lobatón, Juan Tomás de Yegros y Ledesma, Toribio Viaña, Pedro Benítez y Robles, Francisco de Isasi, Melchor Marín, and José González Ríos.
  - 1776 González y Escobar, Juan Francisco Amansio. Advertencias convens. pa. las precaucs. y cautelas de la tropa convinada. Melódia, September 14, 1787. 4 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 46-49. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional [de Asunción], Vol. 3421. (Box [MG 546bj])
    Indian situation; data on following Indian leaders: Lemóy, Chagiú, Tesquingot, Amoó, Tencapín, Lapetá, Yaonfayó, Teonetí, and Cocheahá.
  - 1777 _____. [Carta a Joaquín de Alós y Bru.] Melódia, September 14, 1787. 2 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 17v-18. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional [de Asunción], Vol. 3420. (Box [MG 546y])
    Guarding of passes by Machicuis; punishment of Lenguas and Enimagás.
  - 1778 _____. [Carta a Joaquín de Alós.] Asunción, September 16, 1787. 2 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 34-35. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional [de Asunción], Vol. 3420. (Box [MG 546au])
    Need for provisions at Presidios of Manduvirán, Arecutacuá, and Peñón.
  - 1779 _____. [Carta a Joaquín de Alós.] September 17, 1787. 2 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 16v-17. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional [de Asunción], Vol. 3420. (Box [MG 546x])
    Contemplated trip into Chaco; cattle owned by Enimagás and Lenguas.
  - 1780 _____. [Carta a Joaquín de Alós y Brú.] Melódia, September 21, 1787. 2 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 31v-32. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional [de Asunción], Vol. 3420. (Box [MG 546aq])
    Slow progress at Presidio de San Sebastián and El Peñón; provision of beeves for Villena.
  - 1781 _____. [Carta a Joaquín de Alós.] Melódia, September 27, 1787. 1 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 36. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional [de Asunción], Vol. 3420. (Box [MG 546aw])
    Flight of friendly Indians; desire to leave Hernando Rosas as chaplain in charge.
  - 1782 _____. [Carta a Joaquín de Alós.] Melódia, September 27, 1787. 2 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 59v-60. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional [de Asunción], Vol. 3421. (Box [MG 546bp])
    Report of illness and conferences with representatives of the Lenguas, Machicuis, Enimagás, Tobas, and Pitilayas.
  - 1783 _____. [Carta a Joaquín de Alós y Brú.] Melódia, September 27, 1787. 2 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 11v-12. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional [de Asunción], Vol. 3420. (Box [MG 546r])
    Orders to remain on defensive.
  - 1784 _____. [Carta sin dirección.] Melódia, September 28, 1787. 2 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 58v-59. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional, [de Asunción], Vol. 3421. (Box [MG 546bn])
    Receipt of arms from Luis Ventura (?) Flecha.
  - 1785 _____. [Carta a Joaquín de Alós.] September 29, 1787. 3 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 18-21. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional [de Asunción], Vol. 3420. (Box [MG 546aa])
    Delegation from Lenguas; refusal to pardon rebel Lemoy; surrender of some stolen property.
  - 1786 Mendiola, Francisco and Francisco Ricarte. [Carta al intendente dando cuenta de ataques por los indios de adentro y suplicando se funde fuerte en Saypurú.] Jacurú, October 14, 1787. 2 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 5-6. Modern copy from AGI 110-1-7-D. (Box [MG 1052d])
  - 1787 López, Tomás. Estado que manifiesta la Expedicion que salio de esta Ciudad de Sta. Cruz de la Sierra el 18 de Octubre de 1787 al mando del Subte. de Infa. del Regto. de Saboya Dn. Josef Buzeta para construir un fuerte en la Cordillera de Chiriguanos en el sitio llamado, Saypurú, 1787. 1 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 4. Modern copy from AGI 110-1-7-D. (Box [MG 1052c])
    Table of human and material resources of the expedition.
  - 1788 González y Escobar, Juan Francisco Amansio. [Carta a Joaquín de Alós.] November 2, 1787. 8 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 51v-58. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional [de Asunción], Vol. 3421. (Box [MG 546bm])
    Representations made by Enimagás, Tobas, and Pitilayas against each other; reinforcement of presidios; expedition of soldiers to reconnoiter banks of Paraguay River; examination of river fords and capture of some Indian leaders.
  - 1789 Biedma, Francisco de. [Carta a Su Alteza sobre el peligro que amenazaban las nuevas Reducciones de Mazaiz, Igmirí, y Tacurú en la vasta Cordillera de Indios Chiriguanos, por la mala fe de uno de los capitanes del Pueblo de Saypurú llamado Maruama.] Santa Cruz de la Sierra, November 2, 1787. 2 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 2-3. Modern copy from AGI 110-1-7-D. (Box [MG 1052b])
    Francisco del Pilar, Francisco de Mendiola, and José de Buceta.
  - 1790 González y Escobar, Juan Francisco Amansio. [Carta a Joaquín de Alós.] Paraíso, November 2, 1787. 2 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 15v-16. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional, Vol. 3420. (Box [MG 546w])
    News of Lenguas rebellion; strength of fort at Paraíso.
  - 1791 González y Escobar, Juan Francisco Amansio and José del Casal. [Carta a Joaquín de Alós.] Melódia, November 5, 1787. 2 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 12v-13. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional, Vol. 3420. (Box [MG 546s])
    Return of stolen horses; capture of rebel Tencapín; receipt of munitions.
  - 1792 González y Escobar, Juan Francisco Amansio. [Carta a Joaquín de Alós.] Melódia, November 6, 1787. 2 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 33v-34. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional, Vol. 3420. (Box [MG 546at])
    Contemplated removal of captives.
  - 1793 _____. [Carta a Joaquín de Alós.] November 7, 1787. 1 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 22. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional, Vol. 3420. (Box [MG 546ac])
    Transfer of captive Payené to Alós; with privilege to extend greeting in his native language, with its translation.
  - 1794 _____. [Carta a Joaquín de Alós.] Paraíso, November 8, 1787. 2 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 35-36. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional, Vol. 3420. (Box [MG 546av])
    Fortification of and supplies for presidios of Peñón, Arecutacuá, and Castillo.
  - 1795 _____. [Carta a Joaquín de Alós.] November 10, 1787. 2 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 14-15. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional, Vol. 3420. (Box [MG 546u])
    Receipt of ammunition; attempts to trade prisoners with Indians.
  - 1796 Alós y Brú, Joaquín. [Carta al Marqués de Sonora sobre curiosidades de la historia natural del Paraguay.] Asunción, November 13, 1787. 5 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 1-5. Modern copy from AGI 145-7-24-A. (Box [MG 1470a])
    Activities of Félix de Azara and Eugenio Izquierdo, Director del Gabinete de Historia Natural.
  - 1797 _____. [Carta a S. M. en que] da cuenta de la Reduccion que esta erigiendo frente de esta Ciudad... El asalto que dieron varios Indios hostiles.... Asunción, November 13, 1787. 13 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 124-4-7. (Box [MG 1115])
    Work and merits of José Antonio Yegros, José de Espínola, and Francisco Amansio González.
  - 1798 González y Escobar, Juan Francisco Amansio. [Carta a Joaquín de Alós.] Melódia, November 18, 1787. 1 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 15. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional, Vol. 3420 (Box [MG 546v])
    Rumor of coalition of Machicuis and Enimagás; need for reinforcements.
  - 1799 _____. [Carta a Joaquín de Alós.] [Melódia], November 23, 1787. 2 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 13-14. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional, Vol. 3420. (Box [MG 546t])
    Request to Casal for additional soldiers; need for guard at pass on Río Verde.
  - 1800 _____. [Carta a Joaquín de Alós.] Emboscada, November 29, 1787. 2 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 5v-6. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional, Vol. 3420. (Box [MG 546h])
    Failure of Indians to return; disposition of prisoners.
  - 1801 Alós, Joaquín. [Carta a Antonio Porlier, Ministro de Gracia y Justicia, sobre plantas benéficas de la Provincia.] Asunción, December 8, 1787. 3 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 3-5. Modern copy from AGI 145-7-24-B. (Box [MG 1474b])
    Ibirá and Caraguatá plants in particular.
  - 1802 Rada, Pedro de. Dictamen particular de Rada Disintiendo del comun del Camara de Indias, sobre que se erigiese desde luego en Virreinato la Governacion de Buenos Aires con arreglo a informe de la contaduria general de ellas adjunto y adicionado con notas marginales. Madrid? December 11, 1787. 7 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI — papeles de Estado, Audiencia de Buenos Aires, Leg. 1, No. 45. (Box [MG 1120])
    Review of settlement of provinces of Río de la Plata; list of towns and cities in existence in 1787.
  - 1803 González y Escobar, Juan Francisco Amansio. [Carta a Joaquín de Alós.] Melódia, December 15, 1787. 1 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 5. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional, Vol. 3420. (Box [MG 546g])
    Dispersion of Enimagás.
  - 1804 _____. [Carta a Joaquín de Alós.] Melódia, December 19, 1787. 2 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 4v-5. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional, Vol. 3420. (Box [MG 546f])
    Retreat of Lenguas and Enimagas; capture of Amoó and Gaganijoget.
  - 1805 _____. [Carta a Joaquín Alós.] Paraíso de Melódia, December 23, 1787. 2 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 30v-31. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional, Vol. 3420. (Box [MG 546ap])
    Failure of Indian messengers to return; building of presidio.
  - 1806 _____. [Carta a Joaquín de Alós.] December 25, 1787. 2 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 3v-4. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional, Vol. 3420. (Box [MG 546e])
    War of Lenguas and Enimagás of Tobas in Remolinos region; their treachery at Melódia.
  - 1807 _____. [Carta a Joaquín de Alós.] December 27, 1787. 1 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 1. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional, Vol. 3420. (Box [MG 546a])
    Report of messenger on Lengua and Enimagás Indians; search for Machicuis tribe.
  - 1808 _____. [Carta a Joaquín de Alós.] Melódia, December 29, 1787. 2 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 2v-3. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional, Vol. 3420. (Box [MG 546d])
    Treatment for peace with Enimagás; robberies by Lenguas and trouble with Pitilagas.
  - 1809 Alós, Joaquín. Relacion del tiempo experimentado en los seis ultimos meses del presente año, y demas particularidades.... Asunción, December 31, 1787. 6 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 122-7-1. (Box [MG 851])
    Agricultural products of the country and progress of herds in Provinces of Asunción, Curuguati, Villarrica del Espíritu Santo, Concepción, Ñembucú, Remolinos, and Misiones; cultivation of tobacco, cotton, rice, sugar cane, potatoes, manioc, and corn.
  - 1810 NOMINA DE LOS GOBERNADORES DEL PARAGUAY DESDE SU CONQUISTA 1524 [sic]. 4 l. 22 × 33.5 cm. f. 7-10. Modern copy from unnamed source. (Box [MG 1994d])
    Covering period up to 1787; with incidental biographical data.
  - 1811 González y Escobar, Juan Francisco Amansio. [Carta a Joaquín de Alós.] 1787 (?) 1 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 59. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional. Vol. 3421. (Box [MG 546bo])
    Request for sínodo and help for people under his protection.